<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Anna Notaras and the Byzantine–Venetian Cultural Bridge</title>
        <author>Berk Ateşalp</author>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Ca’ Foscari University of Venice – Digital and Public Humanities Project</publisher>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>Archivio di Stato di Venezia – Exhibition “Le Donne Benefattrici” (Women Benefactors)</title>
            <editor>Michela Dal Borgo; Alessandra Schiavon</editor>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Venice</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Archivio di Stato di Venezia</publisher>
              <date when="2014">2014</date>
            </imprint>
            <note>
              Documentary exhibition highlighting women’s artistic and historical profiles in Venetian archives 
              (15th–18th centuries), curated by <persName>Michela Dal Borgo</persName> and <persName>Alessandra Schiavon</persName>.
              Included archival wills, notarial acts, and letters featuring figures such as 
              <persName>Anna Notaras Paleologhina</persName>, <persName>Veronica Franco</persName>, and <persName>Morosina Morosini</persName>.
              Presented at <placeName>Palazzo Mocenigo di San Stae</placeName>, March–June 2014.
            </note>
          </monogr>

          <relatedItem type="context">
            <title>Francesco Griselini Collection Donation Ceremony</title>
            <note>
              Official handover of <persName>Francesco Griselini</persName>’s works to the Archivio di Stato di Venezia,
              organized by the <orgName>Knights of St. Mark Association</orgName> on 30 May 2014, 
              followed by the exhibition “Francesco Griselini in the Documents of the Venetian State Archives,” curated by <persName>Michela Dal Borgo</persName>.
            </note>
          </relatedItem>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="context">
        <head>Historical Context</head>
        <p>Following the fall of Constantinople in 1453, Byzantine intellectuals, nobles, and clergy migrated toward Venice and other Italian centers. Among them, <persName>Anna Notaras Paleologhina</persName> stands out as a key cultural mediator between East and West.</p>
        <p>She fostered the establishment of the Greek Orthodox community in Venice and supported the construction of <placeName>San Giorgio dei Greci</placeName>, completed in 1573 — a lasting symbol of Byzantine faith and identity within the Venetian Republic.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
